[Music]
the mlan weekly commentary covering
monetary economic and geopolitical news
events now here are Kevin oric and David
melany welcome to the melany weekly
commentary merry Christmas and happy
Hanukkah I'm Kevin oric along with David
melany well David it's fun recording
these programs I had lunch with your son
who is a freshman in college and I told
him I'm thinking back 25 years 26 years
when we had lunch together and what's
happened and then before that you know
me working for your dad what's amazing
is these conversations have turned into
the weekly commentary and as I was
talking to your son I was thinking wow
no wonder there's so many interesting
things to talk about books the things
that we've studied just our thoughts and
dreams moving forward you know the
questions that our clients ask I was
reading through them and I was thinking
they're really family don't you feel
like this is sort of family oh I do it's
an extended conversation it's a lot of
what we experience the two of us when we
get together for the regular commentary
meetings on a Monday afternoon and
evening you know some of the questions
are beyond what I have the capability to
answer so this will be the first Q&A
that we bring in Philip Wartman and
Morgan Lewis to tackle a couple of the
ones that are just right down their
alley I'm looking forward to that well
tell you what let's just go ahead and
get started and I hate to start saying
that John Maynard KES might be right on
something but here's the question dear
Kevin and David John Maynard KES was a
complex human but one thing he got
absolutely right was the relationship
between macroeconomics and Wars you and
Doug Doug Nolan have been warning of
macro risks in China for years now and
we see those warnings playing out in
real time however as China's economy
falters so does their ability to invade
Taiwan are the Chinese still serious
ious and are they a serious military
threat to Taiwan thanks Seth well thank
you Seth yes the Chinese economy has
experienced much slower growth and the
primary source of growth has been
impaired for many years from the real
estate sector even now we're beginning
to see yields on those companies so
their borrowing costs numbers that you
just can't even wrap your minds around
the very best Cas scenario is Vanoni
going from 17 12% to 212% just in the
last 2 weeks
wow and then on top of that you've got
other yields for companies that are 500%
1000% 12,000 and higher so it's
basically saying in that sector is game
over they do still maintain GDP growth
well above that of the US even if you
discount the official statistics by 30
or 40% I would argue that the case for
war does not go away in fact it
increases with economic desperation
there's the aspect of public distraction
on the one hand playing to nationalist
themes and there's also the positive
impact to youth employment what is today
an unemployment problem both inside the
military via conscription and in
manufacturing employment growth as well
for military hardware so discouraged and
unemployed youth need purpose low levels
of inflation in China also leave them
with the latitude to increase spending
and money printing with less immediate
negative impact to their consumers yes
war is inflationary so that's one other
aspect of that John ma kan's
macroeconomic connection between War and
the economy and macroeconomics but the
deflationary Mala they've been locked in
is creating a dynamic which increases
social and political pressure
domestically thus far they've not
announced any radical fiscal measures to
break that Trend and so I think it's
worth keeping in mind that war could
very well be an opportunity to redirect
that negative attention I think they
understand the critical need for Global
demand for semiconductors and other
manufactured goods from Taiwan they may
be inclined to invade Taiwan as if it
were a hostile takeover of an industry
or company not everyone's happy about a
change in management but your suppliers
your vendors your customers if they're
dependent on the products being produced
they may very well go along to get along
they may be waiting for an opportunity
and this is again the People's Republic
of China China maybe waiting for an
opportunity tied to an increased
deployment of US military assets
elsewhere in the world anything that
would leave us stretched a bit thin and
therefore forced to choose our sphere if
you will forced to choose between
commitments for instance if Russia if
they were sort of Unleashed and you know
Hypersonic missiles were used elsewhere
in Continental Europe all of a sudden
our NATO commitments kick in and that
would become by necessity an increased
Focus
then the Chinese might see a window of
opportunity the World Bank and the IMF
have estimated losing Taiwan that
Financial impact to the world in terms
of global GDP 5 to 10 trillion dollar
hit to GDP that assumes you lose
Taiwanese production and it negatively
impacts Global
manufacturing if on the other hand you
maintain access to Taiwanese Goods Now
Chinese Goods you again just new
management the loss is considerably less
and this is where I fear our loyalties
in global loyalties as well are limited
by wanting to maintain the status quo
and are not sufficiently tied to the
current Taiwanese government so in
summary I don't think that ship has
sailed I think the information economy
depends greatly ON Semiconductor
production and we're closer every day to
dealing with new management so control
of that industry would increase the
leverage that China has over the global
economy and yes it stimulates onshore
investment in Tech if you're talking
about how that translates for us here in
the United States we would have to
increase that investment considerably to
insulate from Chinese leverage across
the global economy specifically into
Tech and the information economy but
that kind of capacity shift towards us
domestic production would take time and
take money thanks Seth yeah thank you
this next question is from Chris he says
thank you for all the years of
thoughtful analysis and insights
including the wealth Tri Le framework
can you please say more about the base
of the triangle as insurance in the form
of physical precious metals and discuss
the trade-offs of various approaches
like taking delivery of physical and
storing locally versus investment in
physical bullion ETFs versus products
like vaulted etc etc when considering
the base of the triangle what we call
the perspective triangle we're talking
about insurance the Mandate that we
assigned to that part of the allocation
so we're using insurance that we're
using that term loosely physical Metals
fit that bill the best and I think
that's the case over ETFs which I see as
a reasonable tool you could put it in
the growth side the left side of the
triangle trading for fund and profits
the first question in terms of building
out a physical Metals portfolio is
whether it is static or dynamic that
will inform the allocation mix and the
allocation mix will will inform whether
you want those assets stored or in your
possession or inside a retirement
account structure physical delivery has
been the core of our business for 50
plus years we pioneered physical Metals
in IAS in the 1980s and see that as a
very cost effective way to store as well
as compound ounces as each transaction
as it's traded between metals in order
to increase ounces is done free of
capital gains that has limits though the
limits to that kind of Ira placement are
that only certain products are allowed
into an IRA so the range of ratio and
premium trades is restricted so ideally
you would have a Metals Ira for a few
hundred bucks a year lowers your total
storage costs for metals and allows for
ratio trading on a tax advantage basis
gold to Silver Platinum to platium or
vice versa then outside an irra you
would have other products that again
based on supply and demand see their
premiums expand and contract which
allows for a creative trades ounce gains
after tax some of those trades are
easier to facilitate if metals are
stored at a depository and for others
it's just not necessary thousand ounce
bars to bags of pre-1965 silver coins
would be a case in point just like ETFs
fit better Elsewhere on the triangle
vaulted using the app is a helpful
alternative to cash of course there's no
interest component so in that format you
are giving something up there's an
opportunity cost but it is a way to
denominate a portion of your savings in
what has been a more reliable form of
cash for couple thousand years we have
many clients that split their savings or
have a set percentage of savings in the
vaulted program as well as in their
traditional banking relationships and
certainly vaulted becomes a useful tool
if they're wanting a Metals position but
are already have in mind spending those
proceeds 6 months 12 months 18 months
out for instance if you're looking at
buying a new piece of real estate after
liquidating one but you prefer to wait
temporarily for an attractive purchase
you're not looking to benefit from 1031
exchange vaulted has been a great tool
for funds that are in a holding pattern
where even with the enticement of
interest income not all funds are being
allocated to the traditional bank
account money market fund treasury
position what have you we think the
options that we've just described are
like so many clubs in a golf bag each
one has has a use case and function for
which it's best suited this next
question is from Lynn and we did ask for
an economy of words and this question is
only four words Dave are bonds still
safe thank you thank you Lynn uh it's a
great question if you take higher for
longer as your starting point then the
answer is no if you look at current
spreads on investment grade and high
yield bonds versus treasuries then the
answer is no if you see inflation having
a second move to higher levels which has
been the case in each inflationary trend
of the last 100 years in the US anyway
then the answer is no bonds are not safe
they may be safer than equities in the
capital stack but they are trading
Vehicles today they're not safe
Investments some caveats treasuries
under five years safer treasuries under
two years maturity safer still
high-grade corporates with a maturity of
two to three years I think you could put
in the safer category but investing in
bonds today or any sort of fixed income
is really an interest rate and inflation
bet I'd rather not participate Dave this
next question reminds me of one of my
favorite lunches I just randomly
sometimes go up to the college and eat
in the cafeteria here in Durango and
they had a bookstore and I thought I'm
just going to buy a book I bought the
man who mistook his wife for a hat by
all Sachs and I remember reading that
book going wow everybody needs to read
this you read it this next question
basically says been listening to you
guys for over a decade great show Kevin
used to talk about some catatonics that
only showed Signs of Life when lied to
and so they would laugh uncontrollably
when watching politicians on TV can you
point me to where you heard that it's so
funny I hope it's true do you remember
that Dave oh yeah Oliver saaks is the
author the book The Man Who was took his
wife for a hat I believe the chapter is
on the president's speech and it's about
aphasiacs Zach is a mustre he has an
amazing talent for seeing importance
where others see none neurological
conditions that society would regard as
a deficiency he imbus with dignity by
discussing a counterveiling superpower I
also love the fact that saak was a
distant swimmer I love that had a unique
ability for observing what others don't
take the time to see or to Value yeah
David that's study that saaks talked
about actually was confirmed later and
published in the Journal of nature
saying that there's a 73% of the time
chance that aphasiacs will recognize a
lie versus 50/50 for you and I the next
question Morgan I think you're probably
well suited for this that David Morgan
is known for stating that 90% of the
move in a Metals bull market is in the
final 10% of the Run do you agree with
that statement if so where would you
place Us in this current bull market
relative to its final stage so we could
quibble about that statement by David
Morgan technically but yes the spirit of
his observation is exactly right
historically I also expect a late inning
acceleration and a dramatic period of
outperformance in this current leg of
the gold bull just as we've seen in the
past I'm of the opinion that we're in
another up leg within the same bull
market that powered Metals higher for 12
years you know roughly from 99 to to the
2011 top in my view the same
fundamentals that drove that leg of the
bull are still driving this current leg
so in my view there are a number of
reasons suggesting the potential for
this leg in the gold BT to be even
larger than the last one but as a base
case I would say this leg is likely at
least to be comparable to the last so
that 99 to 2011 bull leg was roughly a
67% 12year trough to Peak bull move
if we match that this time starting from
approximately 1,050 per ounce gold and
that was at the end of 2015 that would
take us to around 8,000 per ounce gold
by somewhere in the ballpark of late
2027 2028 so that might sound surprising
to many but given the fundamental
drivers at work I think that sort of a
move is entirely reasonable to expect
you know one caveat perhaps is that from
99 to 2011 the majority of the years you
had net selling of central banks and
only in 2009 to the present have you had
central banks coming back to the market
as net buyers so if you're looking for
sort of one Dynamic and a fairly
significant one which is shifted it
would be Central Bank participation in
this L yeah certainly agree when I
mentioned a number of reasons to think
that this bull market could be larger
the Central Bank buying to me is
confirmation of the thesis you know as I
said I think this is a continuation of
the the bull market that started in 1999
and I think it began theoretically I
think the market participants were
watching unsustainable policies in
action and buying gold in anticipation
for coming trouble I think that move ran
ahead of itself we had a multi-year
correction but 2008 certainly was a
turning point for Central Bank net
purchases of gold and in fact in 2014 it
became net purchases of gold and selling
of treasuries or at least FX reserves
were increasing gold was getting a
bigger percentage of Central Bank
Reserves and treasuries were losing
ground so to me that it was a
significant fundamental turning point
and after price corrected from 2011 to
the end of 2015 you know I just think
that the next leg of the bull move
kicked into gear the fundamental
confirmation from Central Bank buying
and the fact that we had reached a new
phase where the theoretical problems
that were likely to come in the future
from unsustainable Central Bank policies
by the time we got to the 2015 2016 time
period I think that the theoretical had
started to become actual and certainly
in the last couple years the fundamental
support or the fundamental realization
actualization of problems from
unsustainable Central Bank policies and
fiscal policy as well are now once again
dictating this next move because it is
ual no longer theoretical I think that
potential for this move to outpace the
previous leg of the bull is very
real our next question says I've been
investing in gold for 15 years in
preparation for the upcoming financial
crisis with extraordinary debt levels
and the potential for Sovereign currency
crisis as I watched the way things are
going I'm trying to figure out now
what's the big deal about having gold
when everything else is hitting all-time
highs as well I thought there was
something special about gold and
apparently there's nothing special
anymore as inflation rips higher so will
the markets Bitcoin has now become the
new gold which is amazing to me since it
was made out of thin air and it sounds a
lot like ftic currency please explain
how I went so wrong by doing what I
thought was so right Dave did this
listener do wrong I did the same thing
and I don't know that I feel that way
well we come to conclusions at a point
in time long before time is up or the
story is complete we can do this with
people writing them off based on a set
of circumstances that is truly Limited
in scope we can do that with assets as
well if performance doesn't meet our
expectations within a particular time
frame then we draw conclusion from that
but there is usually more to the story
now there's always more to the story
there is something special about gold
and from ancient Mesopotamia to the
Greek city states to the Roman Empire
the Florence the Gilder the sovereign
gold has an enduring place in all of
history even as history is being written
it's special enough for central banks to
manage their reserves with for wealthy
families to store their wealth in and
for individuals to own even when other
forms of money and credit have surpassed
its current popularity the coincidental
move of gold to higher prices alongside
other assets I don't think that's
permanent either the demand that drives
One Market is not the same which drives
the other
if you change any variable divergences
have and will occur
Bitcoin I would say I disagree is not
the new gold Bitcoin is like so many
other experiments which the markets have
conjured from nothing an asset that
captures enough imaginations to drive
its price higher it's also emblematic of
the current flood of liquidity in the
financial markets which displaces risk
and volatility considerations and
elevates in its Place appetite for high
returns if you change the liquidity
Dynamics the risk appetite shrinks back
considerably and I think you see Bitcoin
for what it actually is I would say
there's nothing wrong with gold its
returns over a one year threee five year
10 year 20 year period more than 4,000
year more than more than acceptable yeah
17 years versus 4,000 years I I think
I'm going to take the 4,000 for at least
some of it but you know it's also worth
remembering that gold is not meant to be
be a speculative vehicle it's meant to
be a stable form of money and as such it
has much more to do with overvaluation
and undervaluation of other assets to
navigate between them right so you want
stable value when you see the price of
gold increasing people think that
something is wrong with the system the
fact that we have yet to see what is
wrong with the system play out within
the financial markets I think there's
your coincidental move to higher levels
some people are speculating price within
the AI craze within cryptocurrencies
within a whole V within anything I mean
this week we've got Apple trading at 41
times earnings that would be an example
of people chasing a trend and other
people are buying gold not because they
think that its earnings are going to
continue to accelerate they think that
there's a reason to own it because
there's something broken within the
system and if I remember right 500 years
ago tulips way outperformed gold oh
absolutely and so there are
opportunities to make money highly
speculative areas it's just worth
remembering that you run out of buyers
and the price trend has turned maybe
before you could have exited philli what
are your thoughts I'm going to drive at
this from a different perspective I'm
usually a data guy but let me enter this
question as a fellow investor who in
2011 bought his first ounce of silver in
a small Jeweler shop at $45 an ounce and
to date has never caught up and yet
couldn't be be happier you know for me
I'm curious as to the underlying heart
of your question did you buy your gold
to preserve your wealth against
potential financial crisis so you could
feed your family keep them safe warm and
secure or was your focus to beat the
market you see I buy gold
indiscriminately because I know I can
depend on it if and when the financial
crisis occurs I don't want it to come I
would prefer we as a citizenry make wise
decisions we would lower our government
debt and don't overextend ourselves but
on the off chance that doesn't become a
reality I have my insurance and the best
part of my insurance is I don't have to
think about it as David mentioned you
can take any snapshot of time and show
Gold outperforming the market or
underperforming the market but as you
kind of pointed out gold is performing
alongside everything else did you spend
time ringing your hands to choose the
right time to buy and manage your
exposure over the last 15 years likely
not hopefully that means on the years
where your gold out performed you were
enjoying life while hedge fund managers
with billions of dollars in assets were
under enormous amounts of stress yeah
this comes back to the perspective
triangle and mandates that we assign to
different parts of your portfolio having
different expectations is entirely
appropriate we have liquidity within the
portfolio it's the right hand side of
the prospective triangle and that
liquidity function gives you certainly
optionality the ability to put that
money to work work whenever you want
from an opportunistic standpoint but it
also allows you to manage a business a
household take care of unforeseen things
whether it's a car that breaks down or a
trip that you want to take and you don't
have to rearrange your finances in order
to do that liquidity is its own mandate
insurance is its own mandate growth in
income is its own mandate so I think a
part of it is balancing expectations
between what you're asking your assets
to do and how well they're doing that
and when it comes to bitcoin I would
take heart cuz while there's an
incredible amount of speculation there
are investors in that environment who
are owning it with the same perspective
in which you own gold which is the
insurance piece now when their insurance
fails they'll be entering to the real
Bastion of insurance which I think gets
understated in the
environment now if your goals and
priorities were to beat the market in
this period of time we do have a
wonderful team here at mlan wealth
management they specialize in hard
assets and they'd love to take the time
to speak with you help you realize those
goals too thanks philli and Morgan it's
nice to have you guys on the show this
year that's awesome so next question
this next question is from Dave north of
the Border cico Corp has a consensus
rating of strong buy which is based on
10 buy ratings zero hold zero sell
ratings the average price Target is 86
Canadian price earnings ratio is
320 that seems almost cartoonish to me
as a healthy PE should be around 20 or
so I thought what am I miss missing here
when every major broker says something
is a buy but I can't see that there are
other companies with outlandishly high
PE ratios they're not as egregious as
camoo that are also considered strong
buys Philip first of all what is camoo
why would it be of interest to us full
disclosure we have a small percentage
allocation within our managed portfolios
to it but wouldn't necessarily recommend
taking a new position maybe you can fill
some of that out before we go into the
valuation part of the question so cico
is a uranium minor primarily based out
of Canada they also do have some
Downstream exposure to nuclear fuel
manufacturing and more recently some
activity in nuclear technologies through
a 50% ownership of the westing house
acquisition about 18 months ago one of
the primary reasons why we like the
space in general is because we do have a
belief in nuclear fuel as stable
reliable energy and gameo is the best
producer have the best tier one assets
and the best cost structure compared to
anyone else and do have active operating
minds and a wealth of opportunity to
build and grow up that production in the
future in healthy jurisdictions in very
safe healthy jurisdictions primarily of
course one of our biggest concerns at
this point is the relationship with
kazatomprom 40% joint venture in that
environment and since they've been
having issues bringing production online
it's been harder and harder for cico to
be able to get access to their pool of
uranium that they're supposed to have
contractually so that's that's one of
the reasons what we've run into a few
headwinds in that name and generally we
wouldn't suggest entering that name at
this time okay so on to the question of
valuations this is a fun one often we
focus on the price component in the PE
because it's usually more Dynamic
earnings and fundamentals of a company
are generally more stable therefore when
we see a PE of 35 or 40 for a company
and with potentially a four to 5%
earnings growth rates it's normal to
recognize you're being taken to the
cleaners and and the market buyer is
buying irrespective of value now when
you come across a PE like cico at 292 as
of this recording cartoonish is a pretty
good description on the surface but a
fundamentally focused Observer will flag
that type of position and they're going
to want to dig a little bit deeper so if
I told you as opposed to a 4 to 5%
earnings growth rate for the next 12
months there was a case to be made for a
53% increase in growth over the next 12
months with a company that's been
operating since '96 and has survived and
grown through two bare markets all of a
sudden the denominator your earnings per
share takes on several multiples of
significance than the Market's pricing
factors and this turns a PE of 292 for
an example into 45 you could say that
the metric on the face of it is absurd
but you're talking about the underlying
asset in this case uranium having price
Mobility is that a fair description
absolutely I mean the PE in its current
state is a misnomer and the reason would
be is because the previous performance
of camoo due to macro factors depressing
its ability to earn income is basically
skewing its valuation in what would make
it look like an overpriced manner but it
does offer a prudent investor an
opportunity now there's one cave I
certainly would put on this the analysts
that you're referring to are certainly
inputting several assumptions which may
or may not come to fruition now from my
perspective assuming the analyst
expectations are true and you could
competently say that Ford earnings could
grow 530 for cico at this current price
the current price is still too expensive
so the next level of analysis would say
what did we observe to why there's a
dislocation from peers even with such
gargantuan earning expectations and this
again kind of dovetails back to the AI
considerations to purported Data Center
build Downs for those large language
models are supporting a value
Destruction for the price and I can make
a strong argument that nearly half of
ccj's current pricing could rely on the
expectations of nuclear buildout to
support data centers now this does not
include the enormous regulatory hurdles
that nuclear deployments will need to
overcome so that cico can even service
fuel pulling uranium out of the ground
and actually have that type of support
for coming decades now there is a good
strong analysis that says that there
could be a macro inflection point which
could serve cico for many decades to
come from my perspective there are many
short-term variables which I believe
service headwinds to camoo and though 10
of 10 analysts today say bye I would
tread cautiously probably one of the few
instances Sam clemens's little quips are
correct whenever you find yourself on
the side of the majority it's certainly
time to pause and full reflect that's
certainly a phrase that or something
like it that I was raised with the
majority is always wrong might be
stating it too emphatically but most of
the time yeah exactly and in this
instance if you got 10 analysts saying
bye bye bye that sounds manic that
doesn't sound thoughtful thanks Philip
next question my family has followed
your prospective triangle advice for
over 15 years and now we've retired and
are starting to use the triangle as a
supplemental retirement fund hoping that
it will last about 10 years at current
bullion prices our triangle is now
heaviest on the insurance Side by about
25% how do you decide when to rebalance
the sides of the triang angle thanks
Richard for the question Richard kind
words I appreciate the question there
are two ways to rebalance one would be
on an annual basis just take year end
which gives you the ability to capture
gains and in a lot of instances migrate
those funds and lower your cost basis as
you move from one leg of the triangle to
the other this is in fact how we ran the
numbers in a portfolio oriented for
growth if you said I want to just focus
on that particular mandate
you could have 100% equities and that
would underperform a portfolio of 75%
equities 25% gold with an annual
rebalance over almost any time frame 10
years 20 years or longer time frames and
essentially you're playing off of Gold's
strengths in a period of financial
Market weakness which again would allow
you to own the same Quality Companies
that you're interested in at a lower
basis while taking gains from a Metals
portfolio or the other strategy if you
like the ratios there's the gold silver
ratio comes to mind here is the Dow gold
ratio the second style of rebalancing is
at Market extremes there is no time
frame it's just the simple math of
dividing one asset class by the other we
know historically the Dow gold ratio
often gets to low levels 5:1 6:1 on the
basis of economic or financial Market
swings and in instances where you have
geopolitical events
adding to macroeconomic concerns the
ratio can go as low as 1: one if you're
already heavy in a precious metals
position I think scaling out gradually
at an earlier time frame at a higher
number makes sense 7 to1 6:1 5:1 and
then getting very aggressive on a
lateral move should you see those lower
figures I think that's advisable so be
early do it often if you are
overweighted I think it's worth noting
that you should be overweighted if
performance has been been positive in
the metals and have grown relative to
other assets so this is something that
is a requirement I think for any
precious metals investor though what is
next how do you reduce or scale back
those are the two approaches the former
favors reduction of metals maybe an
increase in cash if you're talking about
the current environment where equities
trading at or near all-time highs is not
particularly attractive and I think this
is a unique situation where equities and
gold have both traded up I think a move
to cash is SM
right now if you're lightning gold and
silver positions with that sort of
annual rebalancing but I think you've
got a long way to go from the current 15
16 to1 ratio down to five or six maybe
we're fortunate enough to see three two
or even 1: one you may find the
opportunity to move from cash and
liquidity to the growth and income side
pretty soon but I'm cautious there right
now I'd be careful with equities well
and if any of our clients would like
help with that I try to do two to three
triangle updates a Year Dave just where
we do talk about rebalancing based on
various needs so this next question said
last year at this time David announced
the development of a vaulted debit card
What's the progress on that roll out
Mark asked that question thanks for
interest the process is taking longer
than I'd like finding the right Bank
partner is the piece that is absolutely
critical for us uh the functionality and
the ability to roll it out is not that
challenging but knowing who we want to
partner with in a long-term relationship
that's pretty critical so rushing that
detail bad idea we'll keep you informed
unfortunately nothing right now this is
a question from Vance I'm a longtime
listener to your weekly podcast and I'm
especially appreciative of your views on
geopolitics and financial news youve
stated repeatedly that the world credit
markets are in a precarious position and
the debt is at an all-time high what do
you believe is the most likely scenario
that would trigger a worldwide collapse
of the debt markets as a resulting
flight into hard assets thanks for the
question Advance collapse in the debt
markets is something that no regulator
or policy maker will stand by and allow
to occur without massive intervention if
they did not intervene the banking
sectors we know it might not survive so
if Financial solvency issues you would
see them emerge for virtually all of
your financial intermediaries so again
you're talking about true collaps not
just in the financial markets but within
the economy the two courses that are
available when you have as much de as we
have sort of that precarious position
described in the question one is you can
default on your debt instantly
deflationary instantly creates solvency
issues for the aforementioned
institutions the alternative is inflate
and I think the policy makers prefer
inflation to default that strategy is in
motion now granted they don't like the 6
7 8 9 10% inflation rates that we've
seen in recent years but if they can
obscure real world inflation via call it
bean counter creativity and then run a
hotter number than officially reported
to alleviate the pressure of too much
debt there's a likelihood that they can
ultimately pay back a good portion of
that debt with cheaper currency if
you're able to combine Financial
repression with inflation and as best
you can designate the losers that allows
the system to avoid collapse and
relieves the pressure from too much debt
so the ideal scenario okay this is from
a command and control perspective it's
one of controlled decay in the form of
currency degradation inflate and direct
as much liquidity as you can to key
players allow the Federal Reserve
balance sheet to double or triple
relieve stress from your cfis your
systemically important financial
institutions back stop your commercial
banks with both liquidity and Regulatory
forbearance so they can remain viable in
essence control everything you can
control prices control interest rates
control access to the exits from the
financial markets this brings in the
issue of Central Bank digital currencies
it is a perfect fit for the financial
repression necessary to guide direct and
control this sort of inflationary path
move towards the Central Bank digital
currency so that all the exits are
locked and every transaction can be
monitored and guided I think here we can
draw from a previous guest on the
commentary Richard bookstaber the end of
the Theory you direct consumer action
via understanding choices and
preferences through Big Data engage
artificial intelligence guide the
economy and arrive at a preferred
outcome deflation brought about by a
collapse in asset prices is forbidden
that's just what academics think and
that's the way policy makers behave so
control what you can control which is
money supply the flow of money through
the system in some regards it's kind of
a China 2.0 oh man that's scary it
sounds like Aldis Huxley and A Brave New
World I hope that we don't have command
and control economies well another year
of great questions Dave you've been
listening to the mlan weekly commentary
I'm Kevin oric along with David melany
you can find us at ml.com
MCV y.com and you can always call us at
this has been the maany weekly
commentary the views expressed should
not be considered to be a solicitation
or a recommendation for your Investment
Portfolio you should consult a
professional financial adviser to assess
your suitability for risk and investment
join us again next week for a new
edition of the mlan weekly commentary
[Music]